I'm a creative technologist
أنا أعمل في مجال الإبداع التقني
and the focus of my work is on public installations.
ويهتم عملي بالمنشآت العامة.
One of my driving passions
وأحدى محفزات المشاعر لي
is this idea of exploring nature,
هي فكرة إستكشاف الطبيعة،
and trying to find hidden data within nature.
ومحاولة إيجاد بيانات مخفية داخل الطبيعة.
It seems to me that there is
ويبدو لي أن هناك
this latent potential everywhere, all around us.
هذه الإمكانيات الكامنة في كل مكان، من حولنا.
Everything gives out some kind of data,
يعطي كل شئ نوع ما من البيانات،
whether it's sound or smell or vibration.
سواء كان صوت أو رائحة أو إهتزاز.
Through my work, I've been
وخلال عملي كنت
trying to find ways to harness and unveil this.
أحاول إيجاد طرق لتسخير هذا وكشف النقاب عنه.
And so this basically led me to
ولذا، قادني هذا في الأساس الى
a subject called cymatics.
موضوع يسمى سيماتكس (cymatics).
Now, cymatics is the process of visualizing sound
الآن، السيماتكس هي عملية جعل الصوت مرئي
by basically vibrating a medium such as sand or water,
في الأساس عن طريق إهتزازه في وسط مثل الرمال أو الماء،
as you can see there.
كما يمكنك رؤية ذلك هناك.
So, if we have a quick look at the history of cymatics
إذاً، اذا ألقينا نظرة سريعة على تاريخ السيماتكس
beginning with the observations of resonance,
بداية من الملاحظات حول الصدى،
by Da Vinci, Galileo, the English scientist Robert Hook
بواسطة دافنشي، جاليلو، العالم الإنجليزي روبرت هوك،
and then Ernest Chladni.
وبعد ذلك آرنست تشالدني.
He created an experiment using a metal plate,
ولقد قام بتجربة بإستخدام لوحة معدنية،
covering it with sand and then bowing it
مغطاة بالرمال، وبعد ذلك تطويعها،
to create the Chladni patterns that you see here on the right.
لصنع أنماط شلادني التي يمكنكم رؤيتها هنا على اليمين.
Moving on from this, the next person to explore this field
وننتقل من هذا، الشخص التالي الذي أستكشف هذا المجال
was a gentleman called Hans Jenny in the 1970s.
هو رجل يسمى هانس جيني في السبعينيات.
He actually coined the term cymatics.
وهو من أخترع مصطلح السيماتكس.
Then bringing us into the present day
وبعد ذلك نقلها لنا الى الوقت الحاضر
is a fellow collaborator of mine
زميل يتعاون معي،
and cymatics expert, John Stewart Reed.
وخبير السيماتكس، جون ستيوارت ريد.
He's kindly recreated for us
وقد قام بالتكرم بإعادة صياغتها لنا
the Chladni experiment.
تجربة شلادني.
What we can see here is
ما نستطيع رؤيته هنا هو
the metal sheet, this time connected to a sound driver
لوحة معدنية، هذه المرة موصولة مع كرت الصوت،
and being fed by a frequency generator.
ويتم تغذيتها بواسطة مولد ترددات.
As the frequencies increase,
وكلما يزداد التردد ،
so do the complexities of the patterns that appear on the plate.
كذلك تزداد التعقيدات للأنماط التي تظهر على اللوحة.
As you can see with your own eyes.
وكما تشاهدونها بعيونكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So, what excites me about cymatics?
إذاً، ما الذي يثيرني حول السيماتكس؟
Well, for me cymatics is an almost magical tool.
حسناً بالنسبة لي، سيماتكس بالفعل أداة سحرية.
It's like a looking glass into a hidden world.
أنها مثل النظر عبر نظارة الى عالم مخفي.
Through the numerous ways that we can apply cymatics,
وعبر الطرق المتعددة التي يمكن عبرها تطبيق سيماتكس
we can actually start to unveil the substance of things not seen.
يمكننا بالفعل البدء في الكشف عن جوهر أشياء غير مرئية.
Devices like the cymascope, which you can see here,
أجهزة مثل سيماتسكوب، التي يمكنكم رؤيتها هنا،
have been used to scientifically observe cymatic patterns.
تم استخدامها لمراقبة أنماط السيماتكس علمياً.
And the list of scientific applications is growing every day.
وقائمة التطبيقات العلمية تزداد كل يوم.
For example, in oceanography,
على سبيل المثال، في علم المحيطات،
a lexicon of dolphin language is actually being created
قاموس لغة الدلافين يتم إنشاؤه
by basically visualizing the sonar beams that the dolphins emit.
بجعل موجات السونار التي تنبعث من الدلافين مرئية .
And hopefully in the future we'll be able to gain some deeper understanding
نأمل أن نستطيع إكتساب فهم أعمق في المستقبل
of how they communicate.
حول كيفية تواصلها.
We can also use cymatics for healing and education.
ويمكننا أيضاً إستخدام سيماتكس للعلاج والتعليم.
This is an installation developed with school children,
هذه المنشأة تم تطويرها مع مدرسة أطفال.
where their hands are tracked. It allows them
حيث يتم متابعة أياديهم. وتسمح لهم
to control and position cymatic patterns
بالتحكم ووضع أنماط سيماتكس
and the reflections that are caused by them.
والإنعكاسات التي تحدث بسببها.
We can also use cymatics as a beautiful natural art form.
ويمكن أيضاً إستخدام سيماتكس كشكل فني طبيعي جميل.
This image here is created from a snippet
هذه الصورة هنا منتجة من مقتطف
of Beethoven's Ninth Symphony playing through a cymatic device.
لسيمفونية بيتهوفن التاسعة ملعوبة عبر جهاز سيماتكس.
So it kind of flips things on its head a little bit.
إذاً فهو نوع من قلب الأشياء على رأسها قيلاً.
This is Pink Floyd's "Machine"
وهذا هو جهاز بينك فلويد
playing in real time through the cymascope.
يعمل في وقت آني عبر سايمسكوب.
We can also use cymatics as a looking glass into nature.
ويمكننا أيضاً إستخدام سايمتكس مثل نظارة زجاجية الى الطبيعة.
And we can actually recreate the archetypal forms of nature.
ويمكننا إعادة صياغة الأشكال التوراتية للطبيعة.
So, for example, here on the left we can see a snowflake as it would appear in nature.
على سبيل المثال، هنا على الشمال يمكننا رؤية رقاقة ثلجية كما تبدو في الطبيعة.
Then on the right we can see a cymatically created snowflake.
ويمكن بعد ذلك على اليمين رؤية رقاقة الثلج المنتجة بواسطة سيماتكس.
And here is a starfish and a cymatic starfish.
وهنا سمكة نجم البحر وأخرى منتجة بسيماتكس.
And there is thousands of these.
وهناك الآلاف من هذه.
So what does this all mean?
إذاً ماذا يعني كل هذا؟
Well, there is still a lot to explore
حسناً، ما يزال هناك الكثير ليستتكشف.
in its early days. And there's not many people working in this field.
وهذه بواكير الأيام. ولا يوجد أشخاص كثيرون يعملون في هذا المجال.
But consider for a moment that sound does have form.
لكن فكروا لوهلة في أن يكون للصوت شكل.
We've seen that it can affect matter and cause form within matter.
ولقد رأينا أنه يمكن أن يؤثر على الموضوع والشكل يتسبب في المسألة.
Then sort of take a leap and think about the universe forming.
بعد ذلك خذ قفزة وفكر حول تشكيل الكون.
And think about the immense sound of the universe forming.
وفكر حول الصوت الهائل الناتج من تشكيل الكون.
And if we kind of ponder on that, then perhaps
واذا فكرنا في هذا نوعا ما، ربما
cymatics had an influence on the formation of the universe itself.
يكون للسيماتكس تأثير على تشكيل الكون نفسه.
And here is some eye candy for you, from a range of
وهذه بعض الصور الجميلة، أنتجها مجموعة
DIY scientists and artists
واسعة من العلماء والفنانين
from all over the globe.
من كل أنحاء العالم.
Cymatics is accessible to everybody.
والسيماتكس متاحة لكل شخص.
I want to urge everybody here to
وأريد حث كل الناس هنا
apply your passion, your knowledge
لتطبيق عواطفكم، معرفتكم
and your skills to areas like cymatics.
ومهارتكم لمجالات مثل سيماتكس.
I think collectively we can build a global community.
وأعتقد أنه يمكننا أن نبني معا مجتمعا عالميا.
We can inspire each other.
يمكننا إلهام بعضنا البعض.
And we can evolve this exploration
ويمكننا تطوير هذه الإكتشافات
of the substance of things not seen. Thank you.
لجوهر الأشياء غير المرئية. شكراً جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)